Poetry
From the Anglo-Saxon Rune Poem (Rune version):
ᚠᛇᚻ᛫ᛒᛦᚦ᛫ᚠᚱᚩᚠᚢᚱ᛫ᚠᛁᚱᚪ᛫ᚷᛖᚻᚹᛦᛚᚳᚢᛗ
ᛋᚳᛖᚪᛚ᛫ᚦᛖᚪᚻ᛫ᛗᚪᚾᚾᚪ᛫ᚷᛖᚻᚹᛦᛚᚳ᛫ᛗᛁᚳᛚᚢᚾ᛫ᚻᛦᛏ᛫ᛞᚫᛚᚪᚾ
ᚷᛁᚠ᛫ᚻᛖ᛫ᚹᛁᛚᛖ᛫ᚠᚩᚱ᛫ᛞᚱᛁᚻᛏᚾᛖ᛫ᛞᚩᛗᛖᛋ᛫ᚻᛚᛇᛏᚪᚾ᛬
From Laȝamon's Brut (The Chronicles of England, Middle English, West Midlands, ca.1190):


An preost wes on leoden, Laȝamon was ihoten
He wes Leovenaðes sone -- liðe him be Drihten.
He wonede at Ernleȝe at æðelen are chirechen,
Uppen Sevarne staþe, sel þar him þuhte,
Onfest Radestone, þer he bock radde.
(The third letter in the author's name is Yogh, once missing from many fonts; CLICK HERE for another Middle English sample with some explanation of letters and encoding).

From the Tagelied of Wolfram von Eschenbach (Middle High German):

Sîne klâwen durh die wolken sint geslagen,
er stîget ûf mit grôzer kraft,
ich sih in grâwen tägelîch als er wil tagen,
den tac, der im geselleschaft
erwenden wil, dem werden man,
den ich mit sorgen în verliez.
ich bringe in hinnen, ob ich kan.
sîn vil manegiu tugent michz leisten hiez.
Some lines of Odysseus Elytis (Greek):

Monotonic:
Τη γλώσσα μου έδωσαν ελληνική
το σπίτι φτωχικό στις αμμουδιές του Ομήρου.
Μονάχη έγνοια η γλώσσα μου στις αμμουδιές του Ομήρου.

από το Άξιον Εστί
του Οδυσσέα Ελύτη

Polytonic:
Τὴ γλῶσσα μοῦ ἔδωσαν ἑλληνικὴ
τὸ σπίτι φτωχικὸ στὶς ἀμμουδιὲς τοῦ Ὁμήρου.
Μονάχη ἔγνοια ἡ γλῶσσα μου στὶς ἀμμουδιὲς τοῦ Ὁμήρου.

ἀπὸ τὸ Ἄξιον ἐστί
τοῦ Ὀδυσσέα Ἐλύτη

The first stanza of Pushkin's Bronze Horseman (Russian):

На берегу пустынных волн
Стоял он, дум великих полн,
И вдаль глядел. Пред ним широко
Река неслася; бедный чёлн
По ней стремился одиноко.
По мшистым, топким берегам
Чернели избы здесь и там,
Приют убогого чухонца;
И лес, неведомый лучам
В тумане спрятанного солнца,
Кругом шумел.
Šota Rustaveli's Veṗxis Ṭq̇aosani, ̣︡Th, The Knight in the Tiger's Skin (Georgian):


ვეპხის ტყაოსანი შოთა რუსთაველი
ღმერთსი შემვედრე, ნუთუ კვლა დამხსნას სოფლისა შრომასა, ცეცხლს, წყალსა და მიწასა, ჰაერთა თანა მრომასა; მომცნეს ფრთენი და აღვფრინდე, მივჰხვდე მას ჩემსა ნდომასა, დღისით და ღამით ვჰხედვიდე მზისა ელვათა კრთომაასა.

Tamil poetry of Subramaniya Bharathiyar: சுப்ரமணிய பாரதியார் (1882-1921):


யாமறிந்த மொழிகளிலே தமிழ்மொழி போல் இனிதாவது எங்கும் காணோம்,
பாமரராய் விலங்குகளாய், உலகனைத்தும் இகழ்ச்சிசொலப் பான்மை கெட்டு,
நாமமது தமிழரெனக் கொண்டு இங்கு வாழ்ந்திடுதல் நன்றோ? சொல்லீர்!
தேமதுரத் தமிழோசை உலகமெலாம் பரவும்வகை செய்தல் வேண்டும்.
Kannada poetry by Kuvempu — ಬಾ ಇಲ್ಲಿ ಸಂಭವಿಸು


ಬಾ ಇಲ್ಲಿ ಸಂಭವಿಸು ಇಂದೆನ್ನ ಹೃದಯದಲಿ
ನಿತ್ಯವೂ ಅವತರಿಪ ಸತ್ಯಾವತಾರ
ಮಣ್ಣಾಗಿ ಮರವಾಗಿ ಮಿಗವಾಗಿ ಕಗವಾಗೀ...
ಮಣ್ಣಾಗಿ ಮರವಾಗಿ ಮಿಗವಾಗಿ ಕಗವಾಗಿ
ಭವ ಭವದಿ ಭತಿಸಿಹೇ ಭವತಿ ದೂರ
ನಿತ್ಯವೂ ಅವತರಿಪ ಸತ್ಯಾವತಾರ || ಬಾ ಇಲ್ಲಿ ||

I Can Eat Glass
And from the sublime to the ridiculous, here is a certain phrase¹ in an assortment of languages:

Sanskrit: ﻿काचं शक्नोम्यत्तुम् । नोपहिनस्ति माम् ॥
Sanskrit (standard transcription): kācaṃ śaknomyattum; nopahinasti mām.
Classical Greek: ὕαλον ϕαγεῖν δύναμαι· τοῦτο οὔ με βλάπτει.
Greek (monotonic): Μπορώ να φάω σπασμένα γυαλιά χωρίς να πάθω τίποτα.
Greek (polytonic): Μπορῶ νὰ φάω σπασμένα γυαλιὰ χωρὶς νὰ πάθω τίποτα.
Etruscan: (NEEDED)
Latin: Vitrum edere possum; mihi non nocet.
Old French: Je puis mangier del voirre. Ne me nuit.
French: Je peux manger du verre, ça ne me fait pas mal.
French (non-formal): Je peux manger du verre, ça me fait pas mal
French (informal): J’peux bouffer du verre ça m’fait pas mal
Provençal / Occitan: Pòdi manjar de veire, me nafrariá pas.
Québécois: J'peux manger d'la vitre, ça m'fa pas mal.
Walloon: Dji pou magnî do vêre, çoula m' freut nén må.
Champenois: (NEEDED)
Lorrain: (NEEDED)
Picard: Ch'peux mingi du verre, cha m'foé mie n'ma.
Corsican/Corsu: (NEEDED)
Jèrriais: (NEEDED)
Kreyòl Ayisyen (Haitï): Mwen kap manje vè, li pa blese'm.
Basque: Kristala jan dezaket, ez dit minik ematen.
Catalan / Català: Puc menjar vidre, que no em fa mal.
Spanish: Puedo comer vidrio, no me hace daño.
Aragonés: Puedo minchar beire, no me'n fa mal .
Aranés: (NEEDED)
Mallorquín: (NEEDED)
Galician: Eu podo xantar cristais e non cortarme.
European Portuguese: Posso comer vidro, não me faz mal.
Brazilian Portuguese (8): Posso comer vidro, não me machuca.
Caboverdiano/Kabuverdianu (Cape Verde): M' podê cumê vidru, ca ta maguâ-m'.
Papiamentu: Ami por kome glas anto e no ta hasimi daño.
Italian: Posso mangiare il vetro e non mi fa male.
Milanese: Sôn bôn de magnà el véder, el me fa minga mal.
Roman: Me posso magna' er vetro, e nun me fa male.
Napoletano: M' pozz magna' o'vetr, e nun m' fa mal.
Venetian: Mi posso magnare el vetro, no'l me fa mae.
Zeneise (Genovese): Pòsso mangiâ o veddro e o no me fà mâ.
Sicilian: Puotsu mangiari u vitru, nun mi fa mali.
Campinadese (Sardinia): (NEEDED)
Lugudorese (Sardinia): (NEEDED)
Romansch (Grischun): Jau sai mangiar vaider, senza che quai fa donn a mai.
Romany / Tsigane: (NEEDED)
Romanian: Pot să mănânc sticlă și ea nu mă rănește.
Esperanto: Mi povas manĝi vitron, ĝi ne damaĝas min.
Pictish: (NEEDED)
Breton: (NEEDED)
Cornish: Mý a yl dybry gwéder hag éf ny wra ow ankenya.
Welsh: Dw i'n gallu bwyta gwydr, 'dyw e ddim yn gwneud dolur i mi.
Manx Gaelic: Foddym gee glonney agh cha jean eh gortaghey mee.
Old Irish (Ogham): ᚛᚛ᚉᚑᚅᚔᚉᚉᚔᚋ ᚔᚈᚔ ᚍᚂᚐᚅᚑ ᚅᚔᚋᚌᚓᚅᚐ᚜
Old Irish (Latin): Con·iccim ithi nglano. Ním·géna.
Irish: Is féidir liom gloinne a ithe. Ní dhéanann sí dochar ar bith dom.
Ulster Gaelic: Ithim-sa gloine agus ní miste damh é.
Scottish Gaelic: S urrainn dhomh gloinne ithe; cha ghoirtich i mi.
Anglo-Saxon (Runes): ᛁᚳ᛫ᛗᚨᚷ᛫ᚷᛚᚨᛋ᛫ᛖᚩᛏᚪᚾ᛫ᚩᚾᛞ᛫ᚻᛁᛏ᛫ᚾᛖ᛫ᚻᛖᚪᚱᛗᛁᚪᚧ᛫ᛗᛖ᛬
Anglo-Saxon (Latin): Ic mæg glæs eotan ond hit ne hearmiað me.
Middle English: Ich canne glas eten and hit hirtiþ me nouȝt.
English: I can eat glass and it doesn't hurt me.
English (IPA): [aɪ kæn iːt glɑːs ænd ɪt dɐz nɒt hɜːt miː] (Received Pronunciation)
English (Braille): ⠊⠀⠉⠁⠝⠀⠑⠁⠞⠀⠛⠇⠁⠎⠎⠀⠁⠝⠙⠀⠊⠞⠀⠙⠕⠑⠎⠝⠞⠀⠓⠥⠗⠞⠀⠍⠑
Jamaican: Mi kian niam glas han i neba hot mi.
Lalland Scots / Doric: Ah can eat gless, it disnae hurt us.
Glaswegian: (NEEDED)
Gothic (4): 𐌼𐌰𐌲 𐌲𐌻𐌴𐍃 𐌹̈𐍄𐌰𐌽, 𐌽𐌹 𐌼𐌹𐍃 𐍅𐌿 𐌽𐌳𐌰𐌽 𐌱𐍂𐌹𐌲𐌲𐌹𐌸.
Old Norse (Runes): ᛖᚴ ᚷᛖᛏ ᛖᛏᛁ ᚧ ᚷᛚᛖᚱ ᛘᚾ ᚦᛖᛋᛋ ᚨᚧ ᚡᛖ ᚱᚧᚨ ᛋᚨᚱ
Old Norse (Latin): Ek get etið gler án þess að verða sár.
Norsk / Norwegian (Nynorsk): Eg kan eta glas utan å skada meg.
Norsk / Norwegian (Bokmål): Jeg kan spise glass uten å skade meg.
Føroyskt / Faroese: Eg kann eta glas, skaðaleysur.
Íslenska / Icelandic: Ég get etið gler án þess að meiða mig.
Svenska / Swedish: Jag kan äta glas utan att skada mig.
Dansk / Danish: Jeg kan spise glas, det gør ikke ondt på mig.
Sønderjysk: Æ ka æe glass uhen at det go mæ naue.
Frysk / Frisian: Ik kin glês ite, it docht me net sear.
Nederlands / Dutch: Ik kan glas eten, het doet mĳ geen kwaad.
Kirchröadsj/Bôchesserplat: Iech ken glaas èèse, mer 't deet miech jing pieng.
Afrikaans: Ek kan glas eet, maar dit doen my nie skade nie.
Lëtzebuergescht / Luxemburgish: Ech kan Glas iessen, daat deet mir nët wei.
Deutsch / German: Ich kann Glas essen, ohne mir zu schaden.
Ruhrdeutsch: Ich kann Glas verkasematuckeln, ohne dattet mich wat jucken tut.
Langenfelder Platt: Isch kann Jlaas kimmeln, uuhne datt mich datt weh dääd.
Lausitzer Mundart ("Lusatian"): Ich koann Gloos assn und doas dudd merr ni wii.
Odenwälderisch: Iech konn glaasch voschbachteln ohne dass es mir ebbs daun doun dud.
Sächsisch / Saxon: 'sch kann Glos essn, ohne dass'sch mer wehtue.
Pfälzisch: Isch konn Glass fresse ohne dasses mer ebbes ausmache dud.
Schwäbisch / Swabian: I kå Glas frässa, ond des macht mr nix!
Deutsch (Voralberg): I ka glas eassa, ohne dass mar weh tuat.
Bayrisch / Bavarian: I koh Glos esa, und es duard ma ned wei.
Allemannisch: I kaun Gloos essen, es tuat ma ned weh.
Schwyzerdütsch (Zürich): Ich chan Glaas ässe, das schadt mir nöd.
Schwyzerdütsch (Luzern): Ech cha Glâs ässe, das schadt mer ned.
Plautdietsch: (NEEDED)
Hungarian: Meg tudom enni az üveget, nem lesz tőle bajom.
Suomi / Finnish: Voin syödä lasia, se ei vahingoita minua.
Sami (Northern): Sáhtán borrat lása, dat ii leat bávččas.
Erzian: Мон ярсан суликадо, ды зыян эйстэнзэ а ули.
Northern Karelian: Mie voin syvvä lasie ta minla ei ole kipie.
Southern Karelian: Minä voin syvvä st'oklua dai minule ei ole kibie.
Vepsian: (NEEDED)
Votian: (NEEDED)
Livonian: (NEEDED)
Estonian: Ma võin klaasi süüa, see ei tee mulle midagi.
Latvian: Es varu ēst stiklu, tas man nekaitē.
Lithuanian: Aš galiu valgyti stiklą ir jis manęs nežeidžia
Old Prussian: (NEEDED)
Sorbian (Wendish): (NEEDED)
Czech: Mohu jíst sklo, neublíží mi.
Slovak: Môžem jesť sklo. Nezraní ma.
Polska / Polish: Mogę jeść szkło i mi nie szkodzi.
Slovenian: Lahko jem steklo, ne da bi mi škodovalo.
Bosnian, Croatian, Montenegrin and Serbian (Latin): Ja mogu jesti staklo, i to mi ne šteti.
Bosnian, Montenegrin and Serbian (Cyrillic): Ја могу јести стакло, и то ми не штети.
Macedonian: Можам да јадам стакло, а не ме штета.
Russian: Я могу есть стекло, оно мне не вредит.
Belarusian (Cyrillic): Я магу есці шкло, яно мне не шкодзіць.
Belarusian (Lacinka): Ja mahu jeści škło, jano mne ne škodzić.
Ukrainian: Я можу їсти скло, і воно мені не зашкодить.
Bulgarian: Мога да ям стъкло, то не ми вреди.
Georgian: მინას ვჭამ და არა მტკივა.
Armenian: Կրնամ ապակի ուտել և ինծի անհանգիստ չըներ։
Albanian: Unë mund të ha qelq dhe nuk më gjen gjë.
Turkish: Cam yiyebilirim, bana zararı dokunmaz.
Turkish (Ottoman): جام ييه بلورم بڭا ضررى طوقونمز
Tatar: Алам да бар, пыяла, әмма бу ранит мине.
Uzbek / O’zbekcha: (Roman): Men shisha yeyishim mumkin, ammo u menga zarar keltirmaydi.
Uzbek / Ўзбекча (Cyrillic): Мен шиша ейишим мумкин, аммо у менга зарар келтирмайди.
Bangla / Bengali: আমি কাঁচ খেতে পারি, তাতে আমার কোনো ক্ষতি হয় না।
Marathi (masculine): मी काच खाऊ शकतो, मला ते दुखत नाही.
Marathi (feminine):   मी काच खाऊ शकते, मला ते दुखत नाही.
Kannada: ನನಗೆ ಹಾನಿ ಆಗದೆ, ನಾನು ಗಜನ್ನು ತಿನಬಹುದು
Hindi (masculine): मैं काँच खा सकता हूँ और मुझे उससे कोई चोट नहीं पहुंचती.
Hindi (feminine):   मैं काँच खा सकती हूँ और मुझे उससे कोई चोट नहीं पहुंचती.
Malayalam: എനിക്ക് ഗ്ലാസ് തിന്നാം. അതെന്നെ വേദനിപ്പിക്കില്ല.
Tamil: நான் கண்ணாடி சாப்பிடுவேன், அதனால் எனக்கு ஒரு கேடும் வராது.
Telugu: నేను గాజు తినగలను మరియు అలా చేసినా నాకు ఏమి ఇబ్బంది లేదు
Sinhalese: මට වීදුරු කෑමට හැකියි. එයින් මට කිසි හානියක් සිදු නොවේ.
Urdu(3): میں کانچ کھا سکتا ہوں اور مجھے تکلیف نہیں ہوتی ۔
Pashto(3): زه شيشه خوړلې شم، هغه ما نه خوږوي
Farsi / Persian(3): .من می توانم بدونِ احساس درد شيشه بخورم
Arabic(3): أنا قادر على أكل الزجاج و هذا لا يؤلمني.
Aramaic: (NEEDED)
Maltese: Nista' niekol il-ħġieġ u ma jagħmilli xejn.
Hebrew(3): אני יכול לאכול זכוכית וזה לא מזיק לי.
Yiddish(3): איך קען עסן גלאָז און עס טוט מיר נישט װײ.
Judeo-Arabic: (NEEDED)
Ladino: (NEEDED)
Gǝʼǝz: (NEEDED)
Amharic: (NEEDED)
Twi: Metumi awe tumpan, ɜnyɜ me hwee.
Hausa (Latin): Inā iya taunar gilāshi kuma in gamā lāfiyā.
Hausa (Ajami) (2): إِنا إِىَ تَونَر غِلَاشِ كُمَ إِن غَمَا لَافِىَا
Yoruba(4): Mo lè je̩ dígí, kò ní pa mí lára.
Lingala: Nakokí kolíya biténi bya milungi, ekosála ngáí mabé tɛ́.
(Ki)Swahili: Naweza kula bilauri na sikunyui.
Malay: Saya boleh makan kaca dan ia tidak mencederakan saya.
Tagalog: Kaya kong kumain nang bubog at hindi ako masaktan.
Indonesian (non-formal): Aku bisa makan kaca dan tidak terluka
Indonesian (slang): Gua bisa makan kaca njirr
Tunjung Dayak: Akuq ulih kumaan kacaq nya bi perah
Chamorro: Siña yo' chumocho krestat, ti ha na'lalamen yo'.
Fijian: Au rawa ni kana iloilo, ia au sega ni vakacacani kina.
Javanese: Aku isa mangan beling tanpa lara.
Burmese (Unicode 4.0): က္ယ္ဝန္‌တော္‌၊က္ယ္ဝန္‌မ မ္ယက္‌စားနုိင္‌သည္‌။ ၎က္ရောင္‌့ ထိခုိက္‌မ္ဟု မရ္ဟိပာ။ (9)
Burmese (Unicode 5.0): ကျွန်တော် ကျွန်မ မှန်စားနိုင်တယ်။ ၎င်းကြောင့် ထိခိုက်မှုမရှိပါ။ (9)
Vietnamese (quốc ngữ): Tôi có thể ăn thủy tinh mà không hại gì.
Vietnamese (nôm) (4): 些 𣎏 世 咹 水 晶 𦓡 空 𣎏 害 咦
Khmer: ខ្ញុំអាចញុំកញ្ចក់បាន ដោយគ្មានបញ្ហារ
Lao: ຂອ້ຍກິນແກ້ວໄດ້ໂດຍທີ່ມັນບໍ່ໄດ້ເຮັດໃຫ້ຂອ້ຍເຈັບ.
Thai: ฉันกินกระจกได้ แต่มันไม่ทำให้ฉันเจ็บ
Mongolian (Cyrillic): Би шил идэй чадна, надад хортой биш
Mongolian (Classic) (5): ᠪᠢ ᠰᠢᠯᠢ ᠢᠳᠡᠶᠦ ᠴᠢᠳᠠᠨᠠ ᠂ ᠨᠠᠳᠤᠷ ᠬᠣᠤᠷᠠᠳᠠᠢ ᠪᠢᠰᠢ
Dzongkha: (NEEDED)
Nepali: ﻿म काँच खान सक्छू र मलाई केहि नी हुन्‍न् ।
Tibetan: ཤེལ་སྒོ་ཟ་ནས་ང་ན་གི་མ་རེད།
Chinese: 我能吞下玻璃而不伤身体。
Chinese (Traditional): 我能吞下玻璃而不傷身體。
Taiwanese(6): Góa ē-tàng chia̍h po-lê, mā bē tio̍h-siong.
Japanese: 私はガラスを食べられます。それは私を傷つけません。
Korean: 나는 유리를 먹을 수 있어요. 그래도 아프지 않아요
Bislama: Mi save kakae glas, hemi no save katem mi.
Hawaiian: Hiki iaʻu ke ʻai i ke aniani; ʻaʻole nō lā au e ʻeha.
Marquesan: E koʻana e kai i te karahi, mea ʻā, ʻaʻe hauhau.
Inuktitut (10): ᐊᓕᒍᖅ ᓂᕆᔭᕌᖓᒃᑯ ᓱᕋᙱᑦᑐᓐᓇᖅᑐᖓ
Chinook Jargon: Naika məkmək kakshət labutay, pi weyk ukuk munk-sik nay.
Navajo: Tsésǫʼ yishą́ągo bííníshghah dóó doo shił neezgai da.
Cherokee (and Cree, Chickasaw, Cree, Micmac, Ojibwa, Lakota, Náhuatl, Quechua, Aymara, and other American languages): (NEEDED)
Garifuna: (NEEDED)
Gullah: (NEEDED)
Lojban: mi kakne le nu citka le blaci .iku'i le se go'i na xrani mi
Nórdicg: Ljœr ye caudran créneþ ý jor cẃran.
(Additions, corrections, completions, gratefuly accepted.)

For testing purposes, some of these are repeated in a monospace font . . .


Euro Symbol: €.
Greek: Μπορώ να φάω σπασμένα γυαλιά χωρίς να πάθω τίποτα.
Íslenska / Icelandic: Ég get etið gler án þess að meiða mig.
Polish: Mogę jeść szkło, i mi nie szkodzi.
Romanian: Pot să mănânc sticlă și ea nu mă rănește.
Ukrainian: Я можу їсти шкло, й воно мені не пошкодить.
Armenian: Կրնամ ապակի ուտել և ինծի անհանգիստ չըներ։
Georgian: მინას ვჭამ და არა მტკივა.
Hindi: मैं काँच खा सकता हूँ, मुझे उस से कोई पीडा नहीं होती.
Hebrew(2): אני יכול לאכול זכוכית וזה לא מזיק לי.
Yiddish(2): איך קען עסן גלאָז און עס טוט מיר נישט װײ.
Arabic(2): أنا قادر على أكل الزجاج و هذا لا يؤلمني.
Japanese: 私はガラスを食べられます。それは私を傷つけません。
Thai: ฉันกินกระจกได้ แต่มันไม่ทำให้ฉันเจ็บ
Notes:


The "I can eat glass" phrase and initial translations (about 30 of them) were borrowed from Ethan Mollick's I Can Eat Glass page (which disappeared on or about June 2004) and converted to UTF-8. Since Ethan's original page is gone, I should mention that his purpose was to offer travelers a phrase they could use in any country that would command a certain kind of respect, or at least get attention. See Credits for the many additional contributions since then. When submitting new entries, the word "hurt" (if you have a choice) is used in the sense of "cause harm", "do damage", or "bother", rather than "inflict pain" or "make sad". In this vein Otto Stolz comments (as do others further down; personally I think it's better for the purpose of this page to have extra entries and/or to show a greater repertoire of characters than it is to enforce a strict interpretation of the word "hurt"!):

This is the meaning I have translated to the Swabian dialect. However, I just have noticed that most of the German variants translate the "inflict pain" meaning. The German example should read:

"Ich kann Glas essen ohne mir zu schaden."
rather than:


"Ich kann Glas essen, ohne mir weh zu tun."
(The comma fell victim to the 1996 orthographic reform, cf. http://www.ids-mannheim.de/reform/e3-1.html#P76.

You may wish to contact the contributors of the following translations to correct them:


Lëtzebuergescht / Luxemburgish: Ech kan Glas iessen, daat deet mir nët wei.
Lausitzer Mundart ("Lusatian"): Ich koann Gloos assn und doas dudd merr ni wii.
Sächsisch / Saxon: 'sch kann Glos essn, ohne dass'sch mer wehtue.
Bayrisch / Bavarian: I koh Glos esa, und es duard ma ned wei.
Allemannisch: I kaun Gloos essen, es tuat ma ned weh.
Schwyzerdütsch: Ich chan Glaas ässe, das tuet mir nöd weeh.
In contrast, I deem the following translations *alright*:


Ruhrdeutsch: Ich kann Glas verkasematuckeln, ohne dattet mich wat jucken tut.
Pfälzisch: Isch konn Glass fresse ohne dasses mer ebbes ausmache dud.
Schwäbisch / Swabian: I kå Glas frässa, ond des macht mr nix!
(However, you could remove the commas, on account of http://www.ids-mannheim.de/reform/e3-1.html#P76 and http://www.ids-mannheim.de/reform/e3-1.html#P72, respectively.)

I guess, also these examples translate the wrong sense of "hurt", though I do not know these languages well enough to assert them definitely:


Nederlands / Dutch: Ik kan glas eten; het doet mĳ geen pĳn. (This one has been changed)
Kirchröadsj/Bôchesserplat: Iech ken glaas èèse, mer 't deet miech jing pieng.
In the Romanic languages, the variations on "fa male" (it) are probably wrong, whilst the variations on "hace daño" (es) and "damaĝas" (Esperanto) are probably correct; "nocet" (la) is definitely right.

The northern Germanic variants of "skada" are probably right, as are the Slavic variants of "škodi/шкоди" (se); however the Slavic variants of " boli" (hv) are probably wrong, as "bolena" means "pain/ache", IIRC.

That was from July 2004. In December 2007, Otto writes again:


Hello Frank, in days of yore, I had written:
> "Ich kann Glas essen ohne mir zu schaden."
> The comma fell victim to the 1996 orthographic reform,
cf. http://www.ids-mannheim.de/reform/e3-1.html#P76.

The latest revision (2006) of the official German orthography has revived the comma around infinitive clauses commencing with ohne, or 5 other conjunctions, or depending from a noun or from an announcing demonstrative (http://www.ids-mannheim.de/reform/regeln2006.pdf, §75). So, it's again: Ich kann Glas essen, ohne mir zu schaden.

Best wishes,
     Otto Stolz


The numbering of the samples is arbitrary, done only to keep track of how many there are, and can change any time a new entry is added. The arrangement is also arbitrary but with some attempt to group related examples together. Note: All languages not listed are wanted, not just the ones that say (NEEDED).

Correct right-to-left display of these languages depends on the capabilities of your browser. The period should appear on the left. In the monospace Yiddish example, the Yiddish digraphs should occupy one character cell.

Yoruba: The third word is Latin letter small 'j' followed by small 'e' with U+0329, Combining Vertical Line Below. This displays correctly only if your Unicode font includes the U+0329 glyph and your browser supports combining diacritical marks. The Lingala and Indic examples also include combining sequences.

Includes Unicode 3.1 (or later) characters beyond Plane 0.

The Classic Mongolian example should be vertical, top-to-bottom and left-to-right. But such display is almost impossible. Also no font yet exists which provides the proper ligatures and positional variants for the characters of this script, which works somewhat like Arabic.

Taiwanese is also known as Holo or Hoklo, and is related to Southern Min dialects such as Amoy. Contributed by Henry H. Tan-Tenn, who comments, "The above is the romanized version, in a script current among Taiwanese Christians since the mid-19th century. It was invented by British missionaries and saw use in hundreds of published works, mostly of a religious nature. Most Taiwanese did not know Chinese characters then, or at least not well enough to read. More to the point, though, a written standard using Chinese characters has never developed, so a significant minority of words are represented with different candidate characters, depending on one's personal preference or etymological theory. In this sentence, for example, "-tàng", "chia̍h", "mā" and "bē" are problematic using Chinese characters. "Góa" (I/me) and "po-lê" (glass) are as written in other Sinitic languages (e.g. Mandarin, Hakka)."

Wagner Amaral of Pinese & Amaral Associados notes that the Brazilian Portuguese sentence for "I can eat glass" should be identical to the Portuguese one, as the word "machuca" means "inflict pain", or rather "injuries". The words "faz mal" would more correctly translate as "cause harm".

Burmese: In English the first person pronoun "I" stands for both genders, male and female. In Burmese (except in the central part of Burma) kyundaw for male and kyanma for female. Using here a fully-compliant Unicode Burmese font -- sadly one and only one Padauk Graphite font exists -- rendering using graphite engine. Unicode 4.0 or older standard did not have some medial and vowel character; the second example has them.

From Louise Hope, 22 November 2010:  I decided to have a go at an Inuktitut rendering, mainly in hopes of shaming someone who actually knows the language into coming up with something better. Meanwhile, try this:
ᐊᓕᒍᖅ ᓂᕆᔭᕌᖓᒃᑯ ᓱᕋᙱᑦᑐᓐᓇᖅᑐᖓ
aliguq nirijaraangakku suranngittunnaqtunga

Loosely: I am able not to hurt myself whenever I eat glass.

aliguq >> glass (uninflected because it is the patient of a transitive verb in an ergative language)
nirijaraangakku >> "I eat him/her/it" in Frequentative mood (all one verb with inflectional ending, no affixes whatsoever)
suranngittunnaqtunga >> suraq (do permanent harm) + nngit (verb-negator) + tunnaq (ability) + tunga (intransitive ending, making the verb passive or reflexive)

See above about someone who knows the language, et cetera.

Script trivia: the syllable ᙱ is a single unicode character representing the two elements ᓐ (syllable-final n) and ᖏ (syllable ngi). I think they just did it that way because it looks tidier than the expected ᓐᖏ. If your operating system didn't come with Euphemia (all-purpose UCAS font), you can download Pigiarniq. It comes with a jolly little inuksuk ᐀ that the Unicode Consortium is trying to make into a squatter.


The Quick Brown Fox... Pangrams
The "I can eat glass" sentences do not necessarily show off the orthography of each language to best advantage. In many alphabetic written languages it is possible to include all (or most) letters (or "special" characters) in a single (often nonsense) pangram. These were traditionally used in typewriter instruction; now they are useful for stress-testing computer fonts and keyboard input methods. Here are a few examples (SEND MORE):

English: The quick brown fox jumps over the lazy dog.
Jamaican: Chruu, a kwik di kwik brong fox a jomp huova di liezi daag de, yu no siit?
Irish: "An ḃfuil do ċroí ag bualaḋ ó ḟaitíos an ġrá a ṁeall lena ṗóg éada ó ṡlí do leasa ṫú?" "D'ḟuascail Íosa Úrṁac na hÓiġe Beannaiṫe pór Éava agus Áḋaiṁ."
Dutch: Pa's wĳze lynx bezag vroom het fikse aquaduct.
German: Falsches Üben von Xylophonmusik quält jeden größeren Zwerg. (1)
German: Im finſteren Jagdſchloß am offenen Felsquellwaſſer patzte der affig-flatterhafte kauzig-höf‌liche Bäcker über ſeinem verſifften kniffligen C-Xylophon. (2)
Norwegian: Blåbærsyltetøy ("blueberry jam", includes every extra letter used in Norwegian).
Swedish: Flygande bäckasiner söka strax hwila på mjuka tuvor.
Icelandic: Sævör grét áðan því úlpan var ónýt.
Finnish: (5) Törkylempijävongahdus (This is a perfect pangram, every letter appears only once. Translating it is an art on its own, but I'll say "rude lover's yelp". :-D)
Finnish: (5) Albert osti fagotin ja töräytti puhkuvan melodian. (Albert bought a bassoon and hooted an impressive melody.)
Finnish: (5) On sangen hauskaa, että polkupyörä on maanteiden jokapäiväinen ilmiö. (It's pleasantly amusing, that the bicycle is an everyday sight on the roads.)
Polish: Pchnąć w tę łódź jeża lub osiem skrzyń fig.
Czech: Příliš žluťoučký kůň úpěl ďábelské ódy.
Slovak: Starý kôň na hŕbe kníh žuje tíško povädnuté ruže, na stĺpe sa ďateľ učí kvákať novú ódu o živote.
Slovenian: Šerif bo za domačo vajo spet kuhal žgance.
Greek (monotonic): ξεσκεπάζω την ψυχοφθόρα βδελυγμία
Greek (polytonic): ξεσκεπάζω τὴν ψυχοφθόρα βδελυγμία
Russian: Съешь же ещё этих мягких французских булок да выпей чаю.
Russian: В чащах юга жил-был цитрус? Да, но фальшивый экземпляр! ёъ.
Bulgarian: Жълтата дюля беше щастлива, че пухът, който цъфна, замръзна като гьон.
Sami (Northern): Vuol Ruoŧa geđggiid leat máŋga luosa ja čuovžža.
Hungarian: Árvíztűrő tükörfúrógép.
Spanish: El pingüino Wenceslao hizo kilómetros bajo exhaustiva lluvia y frío, añoraba a su querido cachorro.
Spanish: Volé cigüeña que jamás cruzó París, exhibe flor de kiwi y atún.
Portuguese: O próximo vôo à noite sobre o Atlântico, põe freqüentemente o único médico. (3)
French: Les naïfs ægithales hâtifs pondant à Noël où il gèle sont sûrs d'être déçus en voyant leurs drôles d'œufs abîmés.
Esperanto: Eĥoŝanĝo ĉiuĵaŭde
Esperanto: Laŭ Ludoviko Zamenhof bongustas freŝa ĉeĥa manĝaĵo kun spicoj.
Hebrew: זה כיף סתם לשמוע איך תנצח קרפד עץ טוב בגן.
Japanese (Hiragana):
いろはにほへど　ちりぬるを
わがよたれぞ　つねならむ
うゐのおくやま　けふこえて
あさきゆめみじ　ゑひもせず (4)